Bobby E. Mayfield Papers VHP2006/15
CCSU Veterans History Project
Robert E. Mayfield Papers
Bulk, 1983-1999
1973 - 2004, 2006
VHP2006/15
CCSU Veterans History Project
12.0 Digital objects 1 interview DVD
This collection details experience of Bobby E. Mayfield who served with U.S. army and Texas Army Nation Guard from 1973 - 2004. He served with various military units related to Communications & Electronics. The collection contains video of an oral history interview, his short biography, and photographs.
Mayfield, Bobby E., (Bobby Eugene), 1950 -
Biographical/Historical note
Bobby Mayfield registered for the selective service in 1969; however, he also wanted to attend college, so he joined the ROTC at Texas A&M. In 1973, Mayfield was commissioned as a signal officer in the U.S. Army, but because the Vietnam War was winding down, he was never deployed. He elected to leave the service in 1978, and became a Biology and Physics teacher at his hometown high school. In 1983, Mayfield joined the Army National Guard in Austin, TX, and became a member of the Signal Corps. He trained at Fort Hood, TX for mainly Cold War communications scenarios. It was also in 1983, that Mayfield received a call about the "Teacher in Space" program at NASA. There he worked with other trainers to send Christa McAuliffe into space. From 1983-1989 he helped design and implement new communication equipment and strategies for the Army National Guard. In 1990, Mayfield began teaching at Seton Hall University as an ROTC instructor, and later began working at the Pentagon. Mayfield was promoted to Colonel in 1999 while working in Atlanta. He also witnessed the Pentagon bombing of September 11th, and describes how he and a colleague wanted to help during the aftermath. Mayfield retired in March of 2004.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for Research
Custodial History note
All manuscripts and photographs donated were digitized and digitally preserved. The donor retained all original manuscripts and photographs.
Online Access
An online exhibition of this veteran's papers can be accessed at project's website
Texas Army National Guard .; United States. Army.; Cold War Era, 1945-1991 -- Personal Narratives; Communications, Military; Fort Hood (Tex.); Military education; Persian Gulf War, 1991 -- Personal narratives, American; War on Terrorism, 2001-2009
- Series I: Personal Papers, VHP2006/15.I
  - Bobby Mayfield's biography, 2000s; VHP2006/15.I.1; 4.0 Digital objects
  - Interview synopsis, Nov. 25, 2006; VHP2006/15.I.2
- Series II: Multi-Media, VHP2006/15.II
  - Subseries A: Still Images, VHP2006/15.II
    - 2nd Lt. Bobby Eugene Mayfield at Texas A&M university, Commissioning Day on college graduation weekend., May 5, 1973; VHP2006/15.II.1
    - Bobby Mayfield (left) and his friend, Dan Higdon, Graduation weekend for Bobby. Texas A&M university, May 1973; VHP2006/15.II.2
      General note
      Dan was not graduating that day but was part of the Cadet Corp.
    - Christa McAuliffe and Bob Mayfield on zero gravity flight. A part of trainning for NASA's STS-51-L mission (Challenger), Oct. 16, 1985; VHP2006/15.II.3; 2.0 Digital objects
    - Bob Mayfield swearing his son, Jason D. Mayfield, into the Army. Recruitment Center San Antonio, TX, Summer 1995; VHP2006/15.II.4
    - Family celebration for Jason Mayfield completion from basic training., Summer 1995; VHP2006/15.II.5
      L-R: Sgt. Todd Love, DV2 Jason Mayfield, Bobby Mayfield Jason had just completed basic training. Todd and Bob attended the ceremony and then went to family celebration at Dixie’s mother’s home (Annie Ruth Irvin). Mesquite, TX (Grandma’s House)
    - Lt. Col. Bobby Mayfield (left) and Sgt. Frank Todd Love, his Stepson. Tuzla Base, Bosnia., Feb. 12, 1998; VHP2006/15.II.6
      Todd was serving in Bosnia at the time. Bobby was stationed in Germany but on a fact finding trip to Bosnia they were able to visit briefly
  - Subseries B: Moving Images, VHP2006/15.IIb
    - Oral history interview with Bobby E. Mayfield, Nov. 25, 2006; VHP2006/15.IIb.1; 1.0 dvd (Disk DVD VHP2006/15, Box VHP Interview 2006)